Chapter 37.
Sunset.
The cabin by the stern windows. Ahab sitting alone and gazing out.
I leave a white and turbid wake. Pale waters, paler cheeks wherever I sail.
The envious billows sidelong swell towelm my track. Let them. But first I pass.
Yonder by the ever brimming goblets rim.
The warm waves blush like wine. The gold brow plums the blue. The diver sun slow
dive from noon goes down. My soul mounts up.
She wearies with her endless hill. Is then the crown too heavy that I wear
this iron crown of lumberye.
Yet it is bright with many a gem. I the wearer see not its far flashings, but
darkly feel that I wear that that dazzlingly confounds. It is iron that I
know, not gold. It is split, too, that I feel. The jagged edge galls me so. My
brain seems to beat against the solid metal. I steel skull mine, the sort that
needs no helmet from the most brain battering fight.
Dry heat upon my brow. Oh, a time was when, as the sunrise nobly spurred me,
so the sunset soothed no more. This lovely light, it lights
not me. All loveliness is anguish to me since I can never enjoy. Gifted with the
high perception, I lack the low enjoying power. Damned most subtly and most
malignantly. Damned in the midst of paradise.
Good night. Good night.
Waving his hand, he moves from the window.
I was not so hard a task.
I thought to find one stubborn at the least, but my one coged circle fits into
all their various wheels, and they revolve. Or, if you will, like so many
antills of powder, they all stand before me. and I their match.
Oh, hard that to fire others the match itself must needs be wasting. What I've
dared I've willed. And what I've willed, I'll do. They think me mad. Starbucks
does. But I'm demoniac. I am madness maddened. That wild madness that's only
calm to comprehend itself. The prophecy was that I should be dismembered. And I
I lost this leg. I now prophesy that I will dismember my dismemberer.
Now then be the prophet and the fulfiller one. That's more than ye, you
great gods ever were. I laugh and hooted ye, you cricket players, you pugilus,
you deaf burks and blinded bendigos.
I will not say as school boys do to bullies, take someone of your own size.
Don't pummel me. No, you've knocked me down, and I am up again, but ye have run
and hidden. Come forth from behind your cotton bags. I have no long gun to reach
ye. Come, Ahab's compliments to ye. Come and see if you can swerve me. Swerve me?
You cannot swerve me, else you swerve yourselves. Man has ye there. Swerve me?
The path to my fixed purpose is laid with iron rails whereon my soul is
grooved to run over unsounded gorges through the rifled hearts of mountains
under torrent beds. Unairringly I rush knots an obstacle knots an angle to the iron way.